Finding Aid for Jabez Thomas Sunderland Papers 1868-1936
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Topical File
  - N
    - Published (various topics) (Box 43)
    - Sunderland (Box 43)
      (published sermons)
    - Unitarianism (Box 43)
      (published tracts and sermons on N topics or by N authors)
  - O
    - Correspondence (Box 44)
    - Unitarianism (Box 44)
      (published tracts and sermons on O topics or by O authors)
  - P
    - Correspondence (Box 44)
    - India (Box 44)
    - Paine, Thomas (Box 44)
      (manuscript of JTS writing on Paine)
    - Patel, V. J. (Box 44)
    - Prostitution (Box 44)
    - Published (various topics) (Box 44)
    - Social issues (Box 44)
    - Sunderland (Box 44)
    - Unitarianism (Box 44)
      (published tracts and sermons on P topics or by P authors)
  - Q
    - Quakers (Box 44)
    - Quackery, medical (Box 44)
    - Quezon, Manuel (Box 44)
      (letter and autographed pamphlet)
  - R
    - Correspondence (Box 44)
      (include Gilbert Reid and Satyananda Roy)
    - India (Box 44)
    - Published (various topics, including radicalism and race prejudice) (Box 44)
    - Sunderland (Box 44)
      (manuscript of essays, etc.)
    - Sunderland, Eliza Jane Read (Box 44)
    - Unitarianism (Box 44)
      (published tracts and sermons on R topics or by R authors)
  - S
    - Correspondence (Box 45)
    - Correspondence-Mrs. Martha Saint John (Box 45)
    - India (Box 45)
    - India-Keshub Chunder Sen (Box 45)
    - Published (various topics) (Box 45)
    - Savage, M. J. (Box 45)
      (Unity Pulpit and Messiah Pulpit; these published sermons available throughout this topical file)
    - Skepticism (Box 45)
    - Slaten, A. Wakefield (Box 45)
    - Social issues (Box 45)
      (include sex education and suffrage)
    - Spiritualism (Box 45)
    - Sunderland (Box 45)
    - Unitarianism (Box 45)
      (published tracts and sermons on S topics or by S authors)
  - T
    - Correspondence (Box 45)
    - Published (various topics) (Box 45)
    - Social issues (Box 45)
    - Sunderland (Box 45)
      (manuscript of essays, published sermon, etc.)
    - Tagore, Rabindramath, 2 folders (Box 46)
    - Theosophy (Box 46)
    - Tobacco (Box 46)
    - Toplisky, Anton (Box 46)
    - Toronto
      - Miscellaneous (Box 46)
      - First Unitarian Church 1901-1906 (Box 46)
    - Trinity (Box 46)
      (pamphlets and manuscript of article about)
    - Unitarianism (Box 46)
      (published tracts and sermons on T topics or by T authors)
  - U
    - Correspondence (Box 46)
    - Published (various topics) (Box 46)
    - Sunderland (Box 46)
      (published articles)
    - Unitarianism, 2 folders (Box 46)
      (published tracts and sermons on U topics or by U authors)
    - Unitarianism in Japan (Box 46)
      (includes photographs)
    - Universalism (Box 46)
    - University of Michigan (Box 46)
      (petition against the showing of veriscope pictures of the Corbett-Fitzsimmons fight, 1897)
  - V
    - Published (various topics) (Box 47)
    - Social issues (Box 47)
      (include venereal disease and vivisection)
    - Sunderland (Box 47)
      (manuscript of letter to the editor of the Universalist Leader regarding published letters of Mr. van Schaik)
    - Unitarianism (Box 47)
      (published tracts and sermons on V topics or by V authors)
  - W
    - Correspondence (Box 47)
      (include Irving Winslow)
    - India (Box 47)
    - Published (various topics) (Box 47)
    - Social issues (Box 47)
    - Sunderland (Box 47)
    - Unitarianism (Box 47)
      (published tracts and sermons on W topics or by W authors)
    - Walkley, Rev. Albert (Box 47)
      (correspondence and manuscript of article about)
    - Washington, Booker T. (Box 47)
      (manuscript of article about)
    - Wendte, C.W. (Box 47)
      (correspondence and article about)
    - Women-manuscript of essay "The Ministry as a Calling for Women" (Box 47)
    - Women in the Ministry (Box 47)
      (manuscript of writings)
  - Y
    - Young Peoples Religious Union (Box 47)
  - Z
    - India (Box 47)
    - Zoroaster (Box 47)
  - Photographs (Box 47)
    (include portraits, some purchased, of Unitarian clergy, literary figures, university professors; also group portrait of the officers and ministers of the Sadharan Brahmo Somaj, Calcutta, January 1896)
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library also has the papers of Jabez Sunderland's wife, Eliza Jane Read Sunderland, and their children Edson, Florence, and Gertrude Sunderland, papers of the Safford and Sunderland family, as well as the records of Ann Arbor First Unitarian Church.
Selective Index to Correspondents
Abernethy, Alonzo, 1836-1915.
1869, 1870, 1872, Dec. 27, 1875, June 24, 1876
Aked, Charles Frederic, 1864-1941.
Mar. 10, 1911
Allen, Joseph Henry, 1820-1898.
1878, 1879, 1880, 1881, 1882, 1883, 1884, May 15, 1886, 1887, Jan. 7, 1898
American Anti-Imperialist, League.
May 6, 1909, Sept. 17, 1910
American League to Limit Armaments.
Mar. 18, 1916 (L. Hollingsworth Wood)
Ames, Charles Gordon, 1828-1912.
1877, 1878, Mar. 10, 1879, Mar. 24, 1880.
Andrews, C. F. (Charles Freer), 1871-1940.
1930, 1932, 1933, 1935
Angell, George T. (George Thorndike), 1823-1909.
1873, 1879.
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
Apr. 29, 1872, July 4, 1895, Mar. 22, 1897, Dec. 10, 1905, Mar.14, 1910
Bagley, John Judson, 1832-1881.
Feb. 21, 1879, Feb. 28, 1879
Baldwin, William Henry, 1826-1909.
Nov. 11, 1872, 1873, 1875, Nov. 10, 1877, Oct. 15, 1878, May 30, 1884, Dec. 5, 1886, Sept. 19, 1898
Batchelor, George, 1836-1923.
1906, 1907
Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950.
Apr. 28, 1925, Jan. 31, 1929, May 16, 1929, 1930, 1931, July 10, 1932, Jan. 20, 1933, Apr. 13, 1933, Dec. 17, 1934, Dec. 13, 1935.
Bose, Jagadis Chandra, Sir, 1858-1937.
Undated, Mar. 8, 1909, Apr. 5, 1910
Bose, Sudhindra, 1883-
Extensive correspondence, 1920's and 1930's
Bowie, W. Copeland (William Copeland)
Correspondence, 1895-1913, July 31, 1918
Brigham, Charles Henry, 1820-1879.
Dec. 9, 1876, Jan. 16, 1877
Canada India League
July 5, 1916, Sept. 30, 1917
Chadwick, John White, 1840-1904.
1877, 1878, 1880, Aug. 16, 1883, 1887, Feb. 5, i890, May 8, 1892, Feb. 20, 1897, Dec. 19, 1900
Chapin, Augusta J. d. 1905.
1878, Mar. 21, 1879.
Chatterjee, Ramananda, 1865-1943.
Dec. 21, 1895, Feb. 1, 1907, Apr. 26, 1907, Mar. 25, 1909, Dec. 9, 1909, Aug. 11, 1910, Feb. 2, 1911, June 1, 1915, Nov. 4, 1915, Feb. 7, 1918, Nov. 9, 1922, Nov. 11, 1922, Sept. 19, 1925, 1928, 1929, 1930, 1931, 1932, 1933, 1934, 1935, 1936
Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888.
Sept. 19, 1075, Mar. 22, 1880, June 16, 1885, Dec. 13, 1886
Collyer, Robert, 1823-1912.
Nov. 30, 1876, Feb. 4, 1878, May 2, 1879, July 7, 1879, July 6, 1882, May 13, 1887, Jan. 16, 1888, Sept. 21, 1896, Nov. 13, 1896, Nov. 17, 1896, Mar. 8, 1900, June 23, 1909, Mar. 10, 1910
Cooke, George Willis, 1848-1923.
1876, 1877, 1878, 1879, 1880, 1881, 1882, 1883, 1884, Mar. 7, 1887, Nov. 31, 1899, 1900, Mar. 1910, Apr. 27, 1918, Jan. 26, 1891, Nov. 13, 1891
Crane, Augustus Warren, 1868-1937.
Sept. 21, 1897
Crane, Caroline Bartlett, 1858-1935.
Nov. 11, 1891, Nov. 22, 1896, Mar, 1910, May 30, 1910, Sept. 19, 1910, Jan. 1, 1932, Nov. 6, 1934, Oct. 19, 1934
Crooker, Joseph Henry, 1850-1931.
Undated, 1877, 1878, 1879, 1880, Dec. 9, 1881, 1882, 1883, Apr. 19, 1884, 1886, 1891, 1898, 1899, 1900, Feb. 17, 1902, Nov. 23, 1903, Mar. 3, 1907, Dec. 29, 1907, 1908, Mar. 10, 1910, Apr. 5, 1911, Oct. 29,1917, Nov. 7, 1917, May 2, 1923, May 14, 1927, 1930, Feb. 4, 1931
Das, Taraknath, 1884-1958.
1925, 1926, 1927, 1928, 1929, 1930, 1931, 1932, 1933, 1934, 1935
De Normandie, James, 1836-1924.
1881, 1882, Feb. 20, 1887
Drummond, James, 1835-1918.
Oct. 30 1889, Aug. 2, 1893
Durant, Will, 1885-
July 8, 1931, Feb. 11, 1932, Sept. 10, 1932
Eliot, Samuel Atkins, 1862-1950.
Feb. 10, 1897, 1898, 1899, 1900, 1902, Dec. 6, 1906, 1907, Jan. 27, 1909, June 24, 1909, Jan. 10, 1910, June 23, 1913, Feb. 2, 1925, Mar. 5, 1927
Everett, Charles Carroll, 1829-1900.
Nov. 11, 1878, Dee. 3, 1878
Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928
Mar. 1, 1898
Foote, Henry Wilder, 1875-1964
Apr. 20, 1907, Mar. 14, 1910, Apr. 1, 1910, May 9, 1910, Oct. 10, 1910, 1913
Friends of Freedom for India
May 14, 1919
Friends of India's Independence
Nov. 12, 1930
Gandhi, Mahatma, 1869-1948.
May 11, 1927, May 4, 1928, June 17, 1928, Sept. 9, 1928, Mar. 6, 1929
Gannett, Lewis, 1891-1966.
June 10, 1929
Gannett, William C. (William Channing), 1840-1923
1877, 1878, 1879, 1880, 1881, 1882, 1883, 1884, 1885, 1886, 1887
Garrison, William Lloyd, 1838-1909.
Jan. 6, 1905, Mar. 28, 1908
Gregg, Richard Bartlett, 1885-
July 7, 1930, Oct. 20, 1930, 1931
Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.
Nov. 3, 1875, Apr. 5, Oct. 10, Oct. 11, 1882, Apr. 20, Oct. 1, 1883, 1884, Feb. 29, 1892, July 28, 1893, Jan. 10, 1894, May 18, 1892
Hay, John, 1838-1905.
May 5, 1899
Herford, Brooke, 1830-1903.
Dec. 2, 1876, Apr. 17, 1878, Nov. 21, 1878, Mar. 6, 1879, Nov. 15, 1880, Jan. 20, 1881, Oct. 28, 1881, Feb. 26, 1882, May 26,1884, June 4, 1884, 1885, 1886, 1887, Apr. 29, 1891, July 25 1897, Dec. 23, 1897, Mar. 30, 1898, Nov. 29, 1899, May 24, 1900, Oct. 31, 1891
Hindustan Association of America
July 27, 1925, Dec. 19, 1928, Nov. 26, 1929, Dec. 9, 1930, Feb. 9, 1932
Hoar, George Frisbie, 1826-1904.
Feb. 13, 1899
Holmes, John Haynes, 1879-1964.
Mar. 2, 1908, Mar. 14, 1910, Oct. 29, 1925, Feb. 18, 1926, Aug, 3, 1926, Oct. 7, 1926, Nov. 11, 1926, 1927, 1928, 1929, 1930, 1931, 1932, 1933
Independence League of India.
July 25, 1929
India Academy of America
1931
India Independence League of America
Feb. 14, 1930, Dec. 8, 1930.
India National Congress. American Branch
1929, 1930, 1931, 1932
India Society of America
Mar. 23, 1925, Apr. 16, 1925, Nov. 24, 1928, Mar. 22, 1929, Nov. 28, 1929, Sept. 10, 1930
Ingersoll, Robert Green, 1833-1899.
Oct. 20, 1877, Mar. 22, 1879
Jackson, Helen Hunt, 1830-1885.
Dec. 3, 1884
Japan Society
Oct. 11, Nov. 9, 1917
Jones, Jenkin Lloyd, 1843-1918
Nov. 18, 1875, Aug. 18, 1876, Jan. 10, 1878, Dec. 1878, 1879, May 10, 1880, Dec. 1, 1880, 1881, 1882, 1883, 1884, Dec. 14, 1885, Sept. 30, 1892, Sept. 21, 1896, Feb. 11, 1898, Sept. 12, 1899, Mar. 30, Apr. 7, 1910, Nov. 17, 1917, Apr. 4, 1918.
Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.
Mar. 2, Mar. 20, Apr. 1, May 26, 1925
King, Judson, 1872-1958
Mar. 30, 1928, 1931
Krishna Menon, V. K. (Vengalil Krishnan), 1897-1974.
July 18, 1932
Ladd, George Trumbull, 1842-1921.
July 17, 1872, Feb. 24, 1873
Lajpat Rai, Lala, 1865-1928.
Mar. 5, 1916, Sept. 11, 1917, Mar. 3, 1925, June 14, 1927, June 24, 1928, Nov. 29, 1921
Mabie, Henry Clay, 1847-1918.
Dec. 4, 1874, May 5, 1875
McMillan, James, 1838-1902.
Feb. 11, 1897
Manny, Frank Addison, 1868-1954.
Jan. 18, 1928
Martineau, James, 1805-1900.
Jan. 26, 1889, June 1, 1895
Mead, Edwin Deak, 1849-1937.
Jan. 12, 1883, Apr. 22, 1909
Mead, Lucia True Ames, 1856-1936.
Dec. 5, 1908, Mar. 11, 1910, May 5, 1930
Michigan Authors' Association
1910
Morehouse, Henry Lyman, 1834-1917.
July 8, 1869
National Liberal League
Apr. 19, 1878, June 13, 1878.
Nehru, Jawaharlal, 1889-1964.
May 7, 1928
Northrup, George Washington, 1826-1900.
1868, 1869, 1870
Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.
June 22, Dec. 5, 1892, 1895, Mar. 10, 1910
Peabody, Francis Greenvood, 1847-1936.
Sept. 27, 1885, Mar. 25, Apr. 9, 1897
Phelps, Myron H. (Myron Henry), 1856-1916.
1907, 1908, 1909, Feb. 8, 1911
Reid, Gilbert, 1857-1927.
1915, May 19, 1927
Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912.
Oct. 8, 1875
Savage, Minot Judson, 1841-1918.
1877, Nov. 30, 1880, June 25, 1881, Feb. 3, June 14, 1882, Mar. 24, Oct. 30, 1883, Oct. 1893, July 22, 1894, Mar. 10, 1910
Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906.
Dec. 12, 1874
Shippen, Joseph, 1839-1923.
1879, Apr. 25, 1881, 1886, 1887, Jan. 10, 1895, Dec. 18, 1899, Dec. 22, 1890, 1891, 1892
Shippen, Rush Rhees, b. 1828.
1875, 1876, 1877, 1878, 1879, 1880, 1881, 1887, Mar. 8, Mar. 13, 1910, Mar. 5, 1891
Simmons, Henry Martyn, b. 1841.
1878, 1879
Singh, Hajom Kissor, 1865-1923.
1891, 1892, 1899, 1900, Feb. 21, Oct. 11, 1908, 1910, Mar. 14, 1911, 1912, 1913, Jan. 5, Nov. 18, Dec. 12, 1914, 1916, July 12, 1917, 1918, Nov. 24, 1920, Oct. 1, 1921
Society for the Advancement of India
1907, 1908, 1909
Strong, Sydney, 1860-1938.
1930, 1931
Sumner, William Graham, 1840-1910.
Dec. 30, 1873
Tagore, Rabindranath, 1861-1941.
July 21, 1927, June 4, 1928
Toy, Crawford, Howell, 1836-1919.
Nov. 11, 1893, Dec. 10, 1897, Jan. 15, 1898
Villard, Fanny Garrison, 1844-1928.
Dec. 16, 1918
Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1947.
May 27, 1929, Sept. 13, 1932
Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.
May 13, May 21, 1895
Wendte, Charles William, 1844-1931.
July 21, 1872, 1875, 1876, 1877, 1878, 1879, 1880, June 23, 1884, Jan. 3, 1886, Jan. 12, 1892, Sept. 21, 1899, 1907, June 10, Nov. 27, 1908, Dec. 21, 1909, 1910, Mar. 27, 1911, Apr. 10, 1911, June 3, 1912, 1913, Nov. 7, Nov. 15, 1915, Feb. 10, Oct. 14, 1926, 1927, 1928, 1929, Aug. 19, 1930, Jan. 7, 1931
Willard, Frances Elizabeth Caroline, 1839-1898.
March 14, 1892
Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
Feb. 3, 1890
Winslow, Erving, 1839-1922.
Aug. 22, 1899, Oct. 1, 1908, Sept. 17, 1910
Wise, Stephen Samuel, 1874-1949.
Mar. 25, 1910, Dec. 28, 1934